Finding Aid for Craig Marks papers, 1951-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Craig Marks papers 1951-2008
Marks, Craig.
2010020 Aa 2
Chief Engineer for General Motors. Instrumental in the development of the hydrogen fuel cell and General Motor’s electric vehicles. Collection documents Marks’s involvement in engineering organizations and his work at General Motors.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection came from Anne Marks (donor no. 10294 ) in December 2009.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Craig Marks was born in Salt Lake City, Utah in 1929. He received Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering from the California Institute of Technology, and continued his education there, earning an MS degree and PhD.
Marks was a Chief Engineer for General Motors, where he was instrumental in the development of the hydrogen fuel cell and GM's electric vehicles, Electrovan and Electrovair. He began work at General Motors in 1956 as Staff Engineer, and held various positions at the company until he left in 1983 to become vice president of Engineering and Technology at TRW's automotive worldwide sector in Cleveland (1983-1990). He held the position of Vice President of Technology and Productivity for the Allied Signal Automotive Sector from 1990-1993. After retirement, Marks became an adjunct Professor at the University of Michigan in the College of Engineering and the School of Business Administration from 1993-2000.
Marks was involved in a number of engineering organizations and companies. In 1985, he was elected to be a member of the National Academy of Engineering (NAE), and he served as the chair for the Committee for the Review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative, Phase 2, and the Committee on the Review of the FreedomCAR and Fuel Research Program. He was a fellow of the Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE). Marks served chairman of the board of trustees of Altarum as well as member of the board of Intermap and Advanced Modular Power Systems (AMPS).
The papers of Craig Marks document his involvement with various engineering companies and organizations, such as General Motors, and his contributions to the development of the hydrogen fuel cell. This collection contains the following series: National Academy of Engineering (NAE); General Motors; Publications and Reports; Organizations, Companies and Conferences; and Personal.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade.; Automobiles--Fuel consumption--Standards--United States.; Electric automobiles.; Fuel cell vehicles.; General Motors Corporation.; Marks, Craig.; National Academy of Engineering. Committee for the Review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- National Academy of Engineering (NAE)
  The National Academy of Engineering (NAE) is a nonprofit institution of peer-elected members that investigates issues in engineering and technology. This organization is a joint administrator of the National Research Council (NRC), which includes the Transportation Research Board (TRB) as one of its six major divisions. Marks was elected to the NAE in 1985, and served as a reviewer for the NRC report on Corporate Average Fuel Economy (CAFE) standards. This series includes his remarks and correspondence concerning this report, as well as materials from the SAE panel. Marks was the chair for the Committee for the Review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative, Phase 2, and the Committee on the Review of the FreedomCAR and Fuel Research Program. The Committee for the Review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative (IVI), Phase 2 was created at the request of the Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS) Joint Program Office and the Department of Transportation (DOT) to conduct a peer review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative, Phase 2, which operated under the NRC and TRB. This series includes materials from the committee meetings and the first letter report.
  - Elections and membership 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting "Emerging Technologies and Ethical Issues," 2003 (Box 1)
  - Tri-National meeting "Electronics in the Automotive Industry," 2005 (Box 1)
  - Reference for Hancock 2004 (Box 1)
  - Symposium on nano-engineering 2001 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 2001 (Box 1)
  - National Research Council (NRC) report on Corporate Average Fuel Economy (CAFE) standards
    - Prepublication copy and Marks's notes and correspondence 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - SAE panel 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - Additional information including technical analysis 2001 (Box 1)
    - Published report 2002 (Box 1)
  - FreedomCAR and Fuel Partnership "Highlights of Technical Accomplishments," 2006-2008 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Review of the FreedomCAR and Fuel Research Program
    - Creation and background information 2004-2005 (Box 1)
    - First report 2005 (Box 1)
    - Second report 2008 (Box 1)
  - Committee for the Review of the Intelligent Vehicle Initiative (IVI), Phase 2
    - Intelligent Vehicle Initiative (IVI) background 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Marks's review of the Second Annual Letter Report for the Phase 1 IVI Review Committee 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Intelligent Transportation Society (ITS) 2002 (Box 1)
    - Department of Transportation (DOT) responses 2002 undated (Box 1)
    - Creation and first meeting 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    - First meeting additional reading materials 1998, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Second meeting
      - Agenda and related materials 1992, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
      - Reading materials 1996-2003 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Follow-up materials 1997, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - Third meeting 2003 (Box 1)
    - First letter report 2003 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 2003 undated (Box 1)
- General Motors
  Craig Marks was a Chief Engineer at General Motors (GM), where he was instrumental in the development of the hydrogen fuel cell and GM's electric vehicles. This series contains information about GM's electric vehicles, Electrovan and Electrovair. Materials include news releases, diagrams and cutaways, news clippings and SAE publications from the Automotive Engineering Congress and Exposition in Detroit. This series also include Marks's correspondence at GM.
  - Electric Vehicles 1966 undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings about the introduction of the electric car 1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Clippings about Electrovan and Electrovair 1967, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Progress report concerning Electorvan and Electrovair 1966
    - Remarks, news releases and pamphlets (Box 2)
    - Diagrams and cutaways (Box 2)
  - Electrovan, Electrovair and electric vehicle SAE publications 1967 (Box 2)
  - Precept and HydroGen1 fuel cell press brief (includes slides) 2000 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Cost versus weight formula 1973 (Box 2)
    - Rotary engine (includes memos and associated reports) 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1978-1983 (scattered), undated (Box 2)
  - Frank J. Winchell 1970-1979 (scattered), undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1971-2003 (scattered), undated (Box 2)
- Publications and Reports
  The Publications and Reports series contains Marks's writings, many of which were published while he was an employee at GM. Materials include publications on the electric car, Engineering Staff Reports and Marks's thesis. Please note that Marks's SAE report on Electrovan is filed under the General Motors series, in "Electorvan, Electrovair and electric car SAE publications."
  - Electric car 1957, 1963, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Fuel Economy 1975, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Staff Reports 1958-1964 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Thesis 1955 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1960-1988 (scattered) (Box 2)
- Organizations, Companies and Conferences
  The Organizations, Companies and Conferences series documents Marks's involvement with engineering organizations, such as the SAE. This series contains material from the board meetings of Advanced Modular Power Systems (AMPS) and the "Eye and the Auto" conference, where Marks was a keynote speaker.
  - Advanced Modular Power Systems (AMPS) board meetings
    - 2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
    - 2002 (Box 2)
    - 2003 (Box 2)
    - Materials concerning the sale of assets 2003 (Box 2)
  - AMPS correspondence 2001-2003, undated (Box 2)
  - AMPS miscellaneous 2000, 2002 undated (Box 2)
  - Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE)
    - Conferences and honors convocations 1988, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1994-2007 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Photographs of Marks with other SAE members, 1984 (Box 2)
    - SAE "X-Prize," 2006 (Box 2)
  - "Eye and the Auto" Conference 2003
    - Keynote address (Box 2)
    - Schedule, list of participants and miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - PowerPoint presentation on "Harm from Traffic Crashes" (Box 2)
  - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM) and Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation (OSAT) 1999-2000 (Box 2)
  - TRW 1983, 1988 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) undated (Box 2)
  - Fuel Cell Summit 2005 (Box 2)
  - Clippings about the Supercar containing quotes from Marks 2002 (Box 2)
  - Japhet School 2003 (Box 2)
- Personal
  The Personal series contains a biographical sketch and an interview of Marks.
  - Biographical sketch 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1967, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Employment and education 1951-1968 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Interview of Marks 1983 (Box 2)